Guide to the Interfaith Cooperative Ministries Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Interfaith Cooperative Ministries records
1969-2015
RG 255
Yale University Divinity School Library
7
17 boxes
These are the official archives of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., an organization established as Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc. in the early 1970s in New Haven, Connecticut. It was an ecumenical organization that sought to build relationships between churches, support the development of social service agencies and programs, and encourage involvement in local, state, and national social justice issues.
Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc
Biographical / Historical
The Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc. (DCM) evolved in the late 1960s and early 1970s from the New Haven Council of Churches. According to a 1970 "Statement of Purpose" the organization sought "To be agents of human empowerment to the disenfranchised in the New Haven area under a theological discipline." DCM approached this mission of empowerment through efforts to build relationships between the several churches, participation and support for the development of social service agencies and programs, and direct involvement in local, state and national justice issues. Agencies and programs for which the DCM provided support include the Columbus House overnight shelter for the homeless in New Haven, the Community Soup Kitchen, Downtown Evening Soup Kitchen and FISH of Greater New Haven for food support, the Greater New Haven Community Loan Fund for housing issues, Sage Services and Interfaith Volunteer Caregivers for support particularly of the elderly, Citizens for Humanizing Criminal Justice, and Connecticut Interfaith Budget Watch.
In 1995, DCM broadened its mission and membership to serve the greater New Haven area and became Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc. Jewish and Muslim communities became members and joined the effort.
In 2015, the ICM membership agreed that it was time to dissolve the organization due to waning interest from its members. Many of the social service agencies that DCM/ICM fostered continue to thrive.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable documentation of ecumenical activities in the New Haven area, the development of social service agencies for the homeless, poor, disenfranchised, and elderly, and religious advocacy for social justice between 1970 and 2015. The role of religious organizations in the establishment of social service agencies and efforts to effect social change is documented in a detailed way. It is likely that these archives provide historical documentation of various New Haven agencies and programs that does not exist elsewhere. The waning of the influence of mainline religious communities and of the ecumenical impulse in general is reflected in the devolution of the ICM, leading to its dissolution in 2015. The amount and completeness of records varies over the years as some of the Coordinators in charge of the DCM/ICM operations were better recordkeepers than others. There is a considerable gap in documentation for the years 1998-2004.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 2015.
Arrangement
I. History of Organizations
II. Board and Committee Records
III. Correspondence and Reports
IV. Program Documentation
V. Publications / Publicity
VI. Financial Records
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Church and social problems; Religion and justice; New Haven (Conn.) -- Church history; Slie, Samuel; Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc; Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc
- History of Organization, I
  - Legal and formational documents
    - Certificate of Incorporation for Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc., including early draft and amendment for change of name, 1971, 1973, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - By-laws and By-law revisions, 1973-2007, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and memos regarding Certificate of Incorporation and By-laws, 1972-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Certificate of Incorporation and By-laws of Center Churches, Inc., (Hartford model for DCM), 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Documents relating to tax-exempt status, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Documents relating to tax-exempt status, including regarding change of name from Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc. to Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 1981-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Documents submitted to State of Connecticut, 1975, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History / membership
    - Annual reports of The Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc., 1974, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Annual reports of The Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc., 1989, 1990, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports of The Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc., 1992, 1993, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Annual reports of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 1999, 2000, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Annual reports of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 2003, 2004, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Annual reports of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 2006, 2007, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Annual reports of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc., 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Annual meeting minutes and documents, 1973, 1977, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Membership meetings, annual meeting minutes and documents, 1981-2013 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Membership meeting related to dissolution of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Statements of purpose, documents related to organizational structure, 1971-2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Narrative histories: interview with Rev. Dr. Samuel Slie, essay by Rev. Edward F. Dobihal, Jr., 1999, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Lists of members, Board of Directors, officers, 1990-1996, no date (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Board and Committee Records, II.
  - Board of Directors
    - Downtown Cooperative Ministry, Inc. - Minutes and meeting documents, 1970 December - 1972 June (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1972 July - 1973 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1973 May - 1974 November (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1976 January - 1976 September (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1976 October - 1977 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1978 January - November (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1979 January - December (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1980 January - December (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1981 January - November (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1982 January - November (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1983 January - November (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1984 January - 1985 November (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1986 January - 1987 December (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1988 January - 1989 November (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1990 January - 1991 November (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1992 January - 1993 November (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1994 January - 1995 November (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, Inc. - Minutes and meeting documents, 1996 January - 1997 November (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 1997 January - December (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 2004 June - 2007 January (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 2008 April - 2010 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Scope and Contents
      Folder includes 2 CDs with digital files of minutes and other documents dating from 2008-2015
    - Minutes, 2011 January - 2012 December (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Minutes and meeting documents, 2013 February - 2015 February (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Steering Committee
    This section contains the contents of a loose-leaf notebook compiled by DCM Coordinator
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1971 May - October (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1971 November - 1972 February (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1972 March - July (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1972 October - December (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1973 January - March 14 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1973 March 29 - December (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1974 January - 1975 November (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1976 January - December (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1977 January - December (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1978 January - 1979 May (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1979 June - 1981 May (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1981 June - 1982 December (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1983 January - 1984 December (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1985 January - 1986 December (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1987 January - 1988 December (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1989 January - 1990 December (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1991 January - 1992 December (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, correspondence, 1993 January - 1994 December (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1995 January - 1996 December (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 1997 January - December (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, meeting documents, 2004 January - 2006 May (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Other committees and task forces
    - Associate Organization and Program Directors' Fundraising Committee, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Cooperative Development Committee / Working Group, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - House Church Committee, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Investor Responsibility Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Membership Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Political and Community Action Committee (PACAC), 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Political and Community Action Committee (PACAC), 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Political and Community Action Committee (PACAC), 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Politics and Poverty Committee, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Program Committee, 1991-1997 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Project Development Committee / Working Group, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Racism Committee, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Regional Interfaith Partnership Task Force, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Regional Interfaith Partnership Task Force, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Religious Partnership Proposal Committee, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Save the Children Special Committee, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Spiritual Development Working Group, 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Worship Committee, 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      See also documentation of worship services in Series IV, Program Documentation
    - Worship Committee, 1979-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Young Adults, Committee Exploring DCM Ministry to, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and Reports, III.
  - Documents, correspondence from early years of DCM, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Including list of activities and reports of Coordinator, William C. Green, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Planning retreats, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Coordinator's report, correspondence, Coordinator's planning calendar, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Including regarding installation of Joanne Whitcomb as Coordinator, resolution regarding Yale strike, correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Planning retreats, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Installation of John E. Kitagawa as Coordinator, correspondence, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Memos, reports of Coordinator, proposal for homeless shelter in New Haven, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Planning retreats, 1981, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Memos, reports of Coordinator, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Including regarding formation of Columbus House shelter and Interfaith Volunteer Caregivers program, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Memos, reports, appointment of interim Coordinator, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Including regarding installation of Samuel N. Slie as Coordinator, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6a)
  - Including regarding admission of Congregation Mishkan Israel to DCM, establishment of revolving loan fund to address housing crisis in New Haven, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Including regarding revolving loan fund program, proposal for churches to address Columbus House shelter overflow, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Including regarding Connecticut AIDS Residence Program proposal, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Proposal for DCM to continue work of Wider City Parish, retirement of Robert Forsberg, 1989-1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Including regarding budget and finance, New Haven Peace Commission, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Including regarding revised By-laws, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, including to elected officials and regarding Shalom People, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, documents, including from Defense Coalition for Melvin Jones, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Retirement of Samuel Slie, appointment of Dexter Cheney as Coordinator, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Coordinator's reports, reports regarding Community Foundation for Greater New Haven grant, Wider City Parish program, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of Coordinator Reed Smith, reports regarding grant from Community Foundation of Greater New Haven, 2002-2006 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Email from Robert Forsberg regarding history of Wider City Parish, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Article regarding dissolution of ICM, letters acknowledging distribution of remaining funds, 2015 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Program Documentation, IV
  - General
    - Responses to survey of affiliated programs, miscellaneous events, 1995-2005 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Citizens for Humanizing Criminal Justice
    Originally known as Citizens for Better Correctional Institutions
    - By-laws, correspondence, reports, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, minutes, reports, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, reports, newsletters, 1986-1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Clergy breakfast / lunch program
    - Announcements, contact information, 1981-1987 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Announcements, contact information, 1988-1994 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Columbus House
    Emergency overnight shelter for men and women in New Haven
    - Correspondence regarding establishment of Columbus House overnight shelter in New Haven, Shelter Development Committee, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Shelter Development Committee / Shelter Management Committee correspondence, reports, by-laws, policies, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Shelter Management Committee minutes and correspondence, lease agreement with Sacred Heart Roman Catholic Church, 1983 January - May (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Shelter Management Committee, Columbus House Articles of Association and By-laws, Board of Directors, 1983 June - December (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Board of Directors documents, application for Certificate of Incorporation, budgets, newsletter, 1984 January - May (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1984 June - 1985 April (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Board documents, newsletter issue, 1994 April - December (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Board documents, reports, 1995 January - May (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Board documents, reports, 1995 July - 1996 April (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Community Soup Kitchen
    At Christ Episcopal Church, New Haven
    - Reports, Board and Executive Committee minutes, By-laws, 1986 - 1987 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Board minutes, reports, newsletters, 1988 - 1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Board minutes, reports, newsletters, 1992 - 1995 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Connecticut Interfaith Budget Watch
    "Statewide coalition of religious leaders if many faiths committed to raising awareness that the state budget is a moral as well as an economic and political document"
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee minutes, brochures, ads, 1999 - 2004 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Downtown Evening Soup Kitchen
    in 1987 DESK began serving evening meals three nights per week, one night at each of the three churches on the New Haven Green: Trinity Church, the First Church of Christ (Center Church) and The United Church.
    - DCM assistance in formation of DESK, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - FISH of Greater New Haven
    Emergency food assistance agency in New Haven
    - Letter to DCM, brochures, newsletters, 1972-1986 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Greater New Haven Community Loan Fund
    See also "Housing issues" sub-series for DCM committee work and studies leading to formation of the GNH-CLF
    - DCM committees and activities leading to formation of GNH-CLF, 1985-1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Committee documents, formation of GNH-CLF, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Committee and Board documents, 1988 January - May (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Grant applications, reports, 1988 June - December (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Board and committee documents, reports, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Board documents, newsletter, reports, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Habitat for Humanity
    - Advisory committee, brochure, article, 1995-1997, no date (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Housing issues
    This sub-series contains research materials related to housing issues, including those contributing to the formation of the Greater New Haven Community Loan Fund.
    - Miscellaneous material regarding housing issues in New Haven, 1973-1989 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Background material related to community loan fund programs, 1984-1988 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "New Haven Housing Study" - prepared for DCM by Elizabeth Swenson, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Reports, including of Greater New Haven United Way Housing and Homelessness Conference, Comprehensive Homeless Assistance Plan, 1987-1991 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Inner City Community Coffee House
    - Steering Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Interfaith Volunteer Caregivers
    - Grant application to Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Interfaith Volunteer Caregivers Program, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee documents, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Successful grant application follow-up, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Publicity, news releases, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Volunteer training materials, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee documents, reports, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee documents, reports, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee documents, reports, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Newsletters, Steering Committee documents, reports, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, Steering Committee documents, reports, 1990-1992 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, newsletters, Steering Committee documents, 1993-1994 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Steering Committee documents, By-laws, Mission Statement, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Sage Advocate Programs / Sage Services of CT
    Programs to assist the elderly
    - Sage Advocate By-laws, proposals for DCM support, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Proposals, reports, program documentation, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Grant applications, Advisory Board minutes, program documentation, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters, proposals, reports, 1977-1980 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Sage Services of Connecticut Board minutes, grant application, By-laws, 1985-1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors documents, reports, newsletter, 1989-1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors documents, program documentation, history booklet "The Sage Story", 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Brochures, Board of Directors documents, 1993-1995 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Shalom People
    A coalition of religious and peace groups in the greater New Haven area
    - Program documentation, including response to Gulf War, 1988-1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Spiritual Wholeness: Body and Soul project
    Demonstration project to provide health information, health screening, referral, treatment, follow-up to at risk African American and Latino persons, particularly elderly women, for which DCM was a sponsor. The project was coordinated by Rev. Edward Dobihal.
    - Grant application, program documentation, 1991-1994 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Vacation Bible School
    - Program documentation, 1982-1993 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Worship services
    - Joint / union worship services, pulpit exchanges, 1970-1990 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Lenten and Easter services, 1973-1994, no date (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day services, 1992-2006 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous services, including for peace, the homeless, military personnel, 1985-1991, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Youth ministry
    - Program documentation, 1971-1973 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Program documentation, 1981 - 1982 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Program documentation, 1982-1983 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Publications / Publicity, IV.
  - "Highlights" newsletter, 1997, 2001-2004 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - "Highlights" newsletter, 2005-2006 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, fact sheets, 1970s-2001 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous: photographs of member churches, "Interfaith" button, graphic items, slide of DCM display at Black Expo, no date (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Financial Records, V.
  - Budgets, reports, audits
    - Budgets, reports, 1972-1979 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Budgets, reports, correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Budgets, reports, correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Budgets, reports, correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Budgets, reports, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Budget, reports, 1990-1994 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Financial statements, audits, 1995-1999 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Financial statements, audits, 2000-2004 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Grants
    - Corporation for National Service grant for Martin Luther King Day service, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Project of Interfaith Cooperative Ministries - Community Mediation Interracial Dialogue Project
    - J.P. Morgan Chase grant for Technical Assistance, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Haymarket People's Fund grant for general support, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - National Conference for Community and Justice grant for the September 11th Fund Community Through Unity Project, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Project in partnership with Community Mediation, Inc.
    - Haymarket People's Fund grant for general support, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Haymarket People's Fund grant for general support, 2005 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Haymarket People's Fund - denied proposals, 2006, 2007 (Box 17, Folder 7)